Guide to the James Boykin Papers, 1950s-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
James Boykin papers 1960-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Boykin, James.
2.5 Linear Feet 1500 Items
Author and scholar of religion and African American studies.
Collection includes Boykin's drafts and published writings on religion, African American history, imperialism, and AIDS. Also contains a small amount of books from his personal library, diplomas and other personal papers, and unidentified microfilm reels.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Boykin Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift.
Biographical Note
James Boykin is an author and scholar of religion and African American studies.
Collection Overview
The collection includes Boykin's manuscripts, drafts, and writings on various subjects including African American history, Black Power, AIDS, and North Carolina history. Contents range from draft to published versions of his many texts. Also includes school records and transcripts, diplomas, and copies of Boykin's dissertation from Heed University. The collection also contains a number of books from Boykin's personal library, covering topics such as African American history and culture, politics, and teaching techniques. The final portion of the collection contains unidentified microfilm rolls, believed to hold copies of Boykin's articles.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Boykin, James H.
African Americans -- History
United States -- Civilization -- African American influences
United States -- History -- Race relations
Religion -- History and criticism
John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Papers, 1950s-2001, and undated, (3 boxes)
  Includes manuscripts, writings, and other materials by Boykin on subjects such as African American history, religious history, imperialism, and foreign relations. Along with his writings, Boykin's papers include lecture notes and drafts, graduate school transcripts, clippings, and diplomas.
  - Manuscripts, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Readings in American History manuscript (Box 1)
  - Spanish manuscript, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Lecture notes and manuscripts (Box 1)
  - Graduate school records and transcripts (Box 1)
  - Publishing, 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1990s (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Writings (Box 2)
    - Genesis of Early Carolina, dissertation, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Separate But Equal proofs, 1951 (Box 2)
    - Inter-ethnic Death Rate Differential in Florida, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Thank God for Black Power, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Political Intrigue in the Establishment of the Identity of Jesus and Mary, 1986 (Box 2)
    - World Blacks: Self Help and Achievement, undated and 1986 (Box 2)
    - Imperialism Theory and Practice, 1987 (Box 2)
    - North Carolina in 1861, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Essays on AIDS, 1994 (Box 3)
    - The Quest for Consensus, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Emerging Trilogy: The Rise of 3 Great Faiths, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Swahili lessons (Box 3)
  - Diplomas and certificates, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Family/Black history materials (Box 3)
- Microfilm, undated, (1 boxes)
  Unidentified microfilm reels; potentially they hold more of Boykin's writings.
  - 9 boxed reels (Box 4)
- Books, (2 boxes)
  Assorted published books from Boykin's personal library, including texts on African Americans in American culture, film, politics, and war, as well as some texts on teaching American history.
  - Books (Box 4-5)